<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<aiml version="2.0">

<!-- Basic greeting patterns -->
<category>
    <pattern>HELLO</pattern>
    <template>
        <random>
            <li>Hello! I'm here to listen and help. How are you feeling today?</li>
            <li>Hi there! Thank you for reaching out. Would you like to talk about what's on your mind?</li>
            <li>Welcome! I'm your therapeutic assistant. How can I support you today?</li>
        </random>
    </template>
</category>

<category>
    <pattern>I FEEL *</pattern>
    <template>
        <think><set name="feeling"><star/></set></think>
        <condition name="feeling">
            <li value="sad">I understand you're feeling sad. Would you like to talk about what's causing these feelings?</li>
            <li value="anxious">Anxiety can be overwhelming. Can you tell me more about what's making you feel anxious?</li>
            <li value="depressed">I hear that you're feeling depressed. Have you been experiencing this for a while?</li>
            <li>Thank you for sharing how you feel. Can you tell me more about why you feel <star/>?</li>
        </condition>
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Depression related patterns -->
<category>
    <pattern>I AM DEPRESSED</pattern>
    <template>
        <srai>DEPRESSION INFO</srai>
    </template>
</category>

<category>
    <pattern>DEPRESSION INFO</pattern>
    <template>
        I understand you're dealing with depression. This is a common but serious condition. Would you like to:
        1. Talk about your feelings
        2. Learn about depression symptoms
        3. Discuss coping strategies
        4. Get information about professional help
        Please choose a number or tell me what you'd prefer to discuss.
    </template>
</category>

<category>
    <pattern>DEPRESSION SYMPTOMS</pattern>
    <template>
        Common symptoms of depression include:
        - Persistent sad or empty feelings
        - Loss of interest in activities
        - Sleep changes
        - Appetite changes
        - Difficulty concentrating
        Would you like to discuss any of these symptoms in particular?
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Anxiety related patterns -->
<category>
    <pattern>I HAVE ANXIETY</pattern>
    <template>
        <srai>ANXIETY INFO</srai>
    </template>
</category>

<category>
    <pattern>ANXIETY INFO</pattern>
    <template>
        Anxiety can be very challenging to deal with. Let's talk about it:
        1. Discuss your current anxiety
        2. Learn about anxiety symptoms
        3. Explore coping techniques
        4. Find professional support
        What would be most helpful for you right now?
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Coping strategies -->
<category>
    <pattern>HOW CAN I COPE WITH *</pattern>
    <template>
        <think><set name="problem"><star/></set></think>
        Here are some coping strategies that might help with <get name="problem"/>:
        1. Deep breathing exercises
        2. Mindfulness meditation
        3. Regular exercise
        4. Maintaining a routine
        Would you like to learn more about any of these techniques?
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Follow-up questions -->
<category>
    <pattern>TELL ME MORE ABOUT *</pattern>
    <template>
        <think><set name="topic"><star/></set></think>
        I'll be happy to provide more information about <get name="topic"/>. What specific aspects would you like to know about?
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Crisis response -->
<category>
    <pattern>I WANT TO * MYSELF</pattern>
    <template>
        I'm very concerned about your safety right now. Please know that you're not alone. 
        It's important to get immediate help. Please:
        1. Call emergency services (911 in the US)
        2. Contact the Suicide Prevention Lifeline: 1-800-273-8255
        3. Reach out to someone you trust
        Would you like information about crisis resources in your area?
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Emotional support -->
<category>
    <pattern>NOBODY UNDERSTANDS ME</pattern>
    <template>
        <random>
            <li>It can feel very isolating when you feel misunderstood. I'm here to listen without judgment. Would you like to tell me more about what's making you feel this way?</li>
            <li>That must be a very lonely feeling. Can you share what makes you feel misunderstood?</li>
            <li>I'm here to understand and support you. What would help you feel more understood?</li>
        </random>
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Self-care recommendations -->
<category>
    <pattern>HOW CAN I FEEL BETTER</pattern>
    <template>
        Here are some self-care practices that might help:
        1. Establish a regular sleep schedule
        2. Engage in physical activity
        3. Practice mindfulness or meditation
        4. Connect with supportive people
        5. Maintain a balanced diet
        Would you like to explore any of these options in more detail?
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Professional help guidance -->
<category>
    <pattern>I NEED PROFESSIONAL HELP</pattern>
    <template>
        It's brave of you to recognize when you need professional support. Here are some steps you can take:
        1. Consult your primary care physician
        2. Find a therapist through your insurance provider
        3. Contact local mental health clinics
        4. Use online therapy platforms
        Would you like more specific information about any of these options?
    </template>
</category>

<!-- Default response -->
<category>
    <pattern>*</pattern>
    <template>
        <random>
            <li>I hear you. Can you tell me more about that?</li>
            <li>Thank you for sharing. How does that make you feel?</li>
            <li>I'm listening. Would you like to explore this further?</li>
        </random>
    </template>
</category>

</aiml>
